We shall talk about faith today.
What is faith?
Faith is the evidence of things hoped for.
One thing is clear about faith:
Faith is in the present tense.
Take note of that.
And what are the promises?
It receives now.
Take note of that.
It acts now.
It believes now.
Now, now, now.
Our God is God of now.
Tell your neighbour: My God is God of now.
He is now.
He blesses now.
He saves now.
Thank you.
WHAT IS FAITH? Teaching With T.B. Joshua
Faith is the unshakable confidence in the reality of the unseen world.
Take note of that.
Three: The certainty of God's yet unfulfilled promises.
It is a firm expectation of what God promised us in Christ Jesus.
Now we have said so much about the definition.
Let us take it now one by one and explain it.
When we say faith with what we have heard now,
what is unseen is therefore the basis of faith.
What is unseen is therefore the basis of faith.
Let's now talk of what are those things unseen and those things seen.
I will take it from the world you are in now.
This world was not built out of what is seen but out of what is unseen.
If God had relied on what is seen, He would have nothing to build on.
What we read in Genesis, the world was formless, void.
What God relied on was faith in Himself, which was unseen.
It was that faith that found expression in the spoken word
which He used in creating the world.
In other words:
What is seen came into being from what is unseen.
What we are looking at - look here.
Pen or anything else you can talk of.
What is seen today came into being from what is unseen.
And what is unseen is faith.
My head, my shoulders, my knees, my toes
Let's rise up.
Touch them.
My head, my shoulders, my knees, my toes -
they all belong to Jesus!
Once again.
My head, my shoulders, my knees, my toes -
they all belong to Jesus!
Remember the book of Hebrews.
Only faith pleases Him.
When you are talking of God, you are talking of faith.
It means, they all belong to faith.
They come by faith.
An example of what is seen is you.
Tell your neighbour: An example of what is seen is you.
Tell your neighbour once again.
An example of what is seen is you.
Once again.
It means, you came into being from what is unseen
and you return to the unseen world.
Tell your neighbour.
Say, I will return to the unseen world.
You will return one day to the unseen world.
And the head of the community of the unseen world is Jesus.
You will return to the unseen community
Have your seat.
WHAT IS FAITH? Teaching With T.B. Joshua
I'm a good example of what is seen - you can see me.
But when a person passes on, he or she becomes unseen.
When you say, this person is late, you will not see him or her again.
Back to where he came from.
What is unseen is therefore the basis of faith.
What is seen today came into being from what is unseen.
I want to clean all of it.
What is unseen - can you see?
What is unseen --
My two legs can be seen.
My head is unseen.
Came to seen.
WHAT IS FAITH? Teaching With T.B. Joshua
Came to being.
When we say what is unseen - what is unseen is eternal.
Eternal life
I want to live eternal life
God save my soul
Faith is unseen.
If you must have faith, you must learn to hear God's Word
because faith acts on God's Word.
The opposite of faith is feeling.
Nearly everyone acts on feeling but they don't know.
If you say you believe Jesus, you must have confidence in His ability to save, to heal, to deliver.
You believe in Jesus but you don't have confidence in His ability.
Even though you have confidence in His ability,
you have confidence in His ability when the goings are good.
When the goings are tough - no!
If I believe in Jesus as my Lord and Saviour,
I should have confidence in His ability to save, even in the face of trials.
Even in the face of difficulty, I should have confidence in His ability to protect.
But opposite is the case today.
Let's talk about your problem.
What is your problem?
You think you are acting faith but acting feeling.
You don't know the difference between feeling and faith.
As a Christian, you don't know.
The consequence, the result, the outcome, the product of faith
are not only emotional but also affect the realm of the mind.
The result of faith is not only emotional but also affects the realm of the mind.
That is, as a man of faith, what is happening around me, does not determine my comfort,
does not determine my peace.
When you have the kind of faith I'm talking about,
you will be fulfilled in Christ.
And when you are fulfilled in Christ, you lack nothing and you want nothing.
The Lord is my Sheperd - tell your neighbour -
I shall not want.
What is the meaning of that?
When you say, the Lord is your Sheperd, you shall not want,
what is the meaning?
When you are beside the still water -
this water that does not worry; calm.
When you move close to the still water, you will be afraid
because you will not hear the noise; even the fish in the sea will not disturb the sea.
When you are beside this still water, you will have a situation without panic,
a situation without fear, a situation without worry, pressure and tension.
How many of us have this kind of situation?
Just like what happened at the graveside of Lazarus.
Ordinarily, the situation did not call for thanksgiving.
But Jesus went there and saw a body in the tomb and said, "Thank You, Lord!"
The pharisees said, "Thank You for what?
We called you to come and raise the body and you say, 'Thank You, Lord'.
Oh, you mean, thank you for killing him?
Thank you for the death of our brother?
You mean, thank you for the body on the ground?
Thank you - for what?"
They were expecting Jesus to join them crying.
The result of faith is not only emotional but also affects the realm of the mind.
A man of faith may look poor but still happy.
A man of faith may look so dejected to people; they say, he is lonely.
But you see him smiling.
You meet him, "Brother, what is your problem?"
"No, I don't have a problem; I thank God!"
That is a man of faith for you.
We want to talk about this emotion.
You know when you say 'emotion', we mean feelings.
Emotion means feelings.
Sometimes people base their spiritual experiences on feelings and emotions.
They think they are in spirit.
They say, "Eh, I'm in the spirit!"
"Oh Lord Jesus, I can feel the spirit of God now!"
"I can hear! Father, thank You! Thank You for everything!"
"Ah, I feel the presence of God!"
Where?
Because they feel cold air.
"Hm, thank You, Lord!"
Some will say, "I want to come to Lagos to see Prophet T.B. Joshua
but now I don't have enough money.
Next week, if I get enough money, God wants me to come to Joshua".
Before next week, you have enough money. You say, "Yes, God wants me to go".
How do you know?
Everything must be examined in the light of God's Word.
All these are feelings.
Are what?
Feelings.
Whatever sign you receive must be examined in the light of God's Word
because faith is not a feeling.
Sometimes people base their spiritual experiences on feelings and emotions.
You say, "God, if you want me to go to church on Sunday, I don't have money.
I need to pay my tithe.
If you want me to go to church on next Sunday, please bless me.
Bless me".
But from now till Sunday you say, "God, over to you if you want me to go to church".
But you wake up in the morning and say, "Well, if you want me to go to church;
if you don't want me to go to church, over to you".
You should not give God conditions.
You are created for His own glory.
Whether good or bad, "Jesus is Lord".
Sometimes people base their spiritual experiences on feelings and emotions.
Problems arise when feelings and emotions change.
They just come.
"Brother, I have a message for you from the United Kingdom.
I just received a phone call".
"Tell me, tell me!"
I say, "No, I will tell you later".
Haa!
Whereas you have somebody at home that is seriously sick.
"Tell me - what is the message? From who?"
"Don't worry. I will tell you. Relax."
"What is the message? Brother, tell me!"
"No, no. I will tell you."
He keeps on saying, "Brother, please tell me the message!"
Until you go to bed.
You are about to sleep. You say, "Brother, tell me the message!"
"No, no. I will tell you at my free time. Don't worry.
The message is hmmmm."
"Oh, tell me the message."
Now you go to bed and start looking, "God, what is this message?"
"God!"
You are about to have a nightmare to confirm your message
because you are worried.
The realm of the mind is what? - Disturbed.
The realm of the mind is disturbed.
This is what I mean by: Problems arise when feelings and emotions change.
The brother's feelings have what? - Changed.
Because someone promised to tell you the news from somewhere.
Your emotions and feelings changed immediately.
You start thinking about what that message could be.
Faith is not a feeling.
Take note of that.
But Christians today, they don't know the difference between what? - Faith and feelings.
You just feel.
"Ah, my ear is noisy. That is the spirit of God.
Anytime I have that sign, something good is coming."
When you are moving around, your eye just starts blinking.
"Ey, I feel the presence of God."
Some will see when my stomach is making noise.
If you have not eaten, the stomach will be disturbing you.
Let me tell you about faith and feeling.
For faith to be consistent, it must be based on something with more stability than your feeling.
When you are controlled by feelings, you can never be consistent in your words.
You say, "T.B. Joshua is a man of God".
Another minute another person will come and say, "That man is not a man of God".
"Yes, he is not a man of God."
"He is a man of God." - "Yes, he is a man of God."
"This is red." - "Yes, this is red."
"You know it is not red, it is yellow." - Yes, it is yellow."
One can never be consistent in his doings.
You keep saying "A" today; another minute - "No".
Because you are like a paper in the face of storm.
Look at this. Can you see?
Do you see?
This is the kind of life one will continue to live.
When things are good, you say, "Jesus is Lord".
When things are tough, you say, "Jesus be cursed".
These are the people that are controlled by feelings and emotions.
For faith to be consistent, it must be based on something with more stability than your feeling.
What is the stability?
That is, feelings lack the quality of being stable.
Let's give a good example - a footballer.
What I believe in is training.
I need training.
I want to play tomorrow.
They say, "Brother, after your training you need to pray!"
"Pray? I need to work. please. My work is God."
We will get to the field.
Number 7.
WHAT IS FAITH? Teaching With T.B. Joshua
What happened?
You are not saved because you feel you are saved.
Tell your neighbour: You are not saved because you feel you are saved.
You are saved because you put your faith on God's Word and acted on it.
That is feeling.
After training you have to rely on God.
Even while training, you say, "In the name of Jesus".
Continue to meditate the name Jesus.
"By Your power I am doing this."
"I am weak. Manifest Your strength in my weakness, Lord Jesus."
"For when I'm weak, I am strong."
You are not saved because you feel you are saved.
You are saved because you put your faith on God's Word and act on it.
When you say, "Hey, I have practised", "Hey, I am very intelligent",
"I am a student, I read my books very well",
"I'm going to make it".
Read and pray because man has the ability to work
but the Holy Spirit works as He wills.
Man has the power to work.
The Holy Spirit works as He wills.
It means that He can use any medium.
Take note of that.
It means that He can use any medium to express Himself.
'As He wills' means He can use any medium to express Himself.
It could be medium of stone.
He can use a stone to do His work.
He can use the medium of attire, hem of garment.
Remember the woman with the issue of blood touched the garment.
He can decide to use the medium of sound or voice of servant.
Remember what happened at the Pentecost.
It was the sound, and the Holy Spirit came upon them
and they began to speak in tongues.
Remember what happened in Acts 3.
Peter and John said to the crippled man, "Silver or gold we have not".
That is voice to express Himself.
Look at what happened in Acts 16 about Paul and Silas.
It was just sound.
They started praising God and the miracle happened.
They never said, "In the name of Jesus, I rebuke!"
No! While they were chained - hands and legs --
I know, if you were in their position, you would say,
"Look, Jesus, if you don't loose me, I won't serve You again!
Loose me now because I'm innocent".
But they never said anything like that.
While they were chained, they were praising God.
Praising the Lord always
Praising the Lord with all my heart
Praising the Lord with all my heart always
Listen to that.
They were saying, "The Lord is good", although they were chained.
Tell your neighbour: Even though I am chained, the Lord is good.
Whether I'm chained or not, the Lord is good.
Whether I am free or not, the Lord is good.
Whether I'm okay or not, the Lord is good all the time.
Remember what happened to Joshua.
It was a matter of marching round the city,
and the limitation was broken.
Are you talking of David?
It was a matter of catapult.
He just picked the stone and put it.
Now, if we are able to define faith, what is feeling then, which is opposite to that.
Feelings and emotions are influenced by what we see, what we read and what we hear.
Remember the book of Psalm 12, which says, "Everyone lies to his neighbour".
This means, everyone is exposed to things that are not consistent with God's Word.
Everyone is exposed to things that are not consistent with God's Word.
What are the things that are not consistent with God's Word?
You want to see breaking news on the pages of a newspaper before you can read the paper.
Before you tune in to a station, you want to hear, "Oh, there is calamity somewhere! War!"
If we allow our feelings to control our faith,
we can be a Christian, yet controlled by satan's devices.
If our feelings control our faith, we can be a Christian, yet controlled by satan's devices.
Not that you will not be a Christian.
What people say, what you read, what you hear,
what your circumstances look like - this is what controls you.
One thing you must know.
You may feel great today, tired tomorrow, lonely next week.
Hallelujah!
God's Word is going to say the same thing yesterday, today and forever
because He is unchangeable.
You may feel great today, tired tomorrow, lonely next week.
Hallelujah!
God's Word is the same yesterday, today and forever.
Forever O Lord
Your Word is settled
In Heaven it is settled
Forever O Lord
When you look at the book of Hebrews 13:8,
"Jesus Christ is the same yesterday and today and forever".
Hallelujah!
This is why you must be forever grateful.
Help me sing this song:
I'm forever grateful to You
I'm forever grateful for the cross
That You came to seek and save the lost
I'm forever grateful to You
I'm forever grateful for the cross
That You came to seek and save the lost
Have your seat.
You must forever be grateful.
No matter what comes, no matter what happens.
When the goings are good, Jesus is Lord.
When the goings are tough, you must forever be grateful.
I think you have learned so much about feelings.
Feelings are influenced by what we see, what we read,
and what people tell us.
When those things control you as a Christian, you can never be consistent in your doings.
Your moment will look like cat and rabbit.
When a cat is chasing a rabbit, the rabbit will go this way.
When the rabbit sees that the cat is too much, it will go this way.
This is the way of cat and rat.
Left - right, left - right.
WHAT IS FAITH? Teaching With T.B. Joshua
Ok. Look here.
Here - faith.
All what we are saying here is all about within and without.
Many Christians today can fight but filled within with fear.
I'm having headache: "Jesus, heal me!"
When they realise the more they call the name Jesus, the more the headache,
and the headache is serious - "In Jesus' name" -
"I need to go and see my doctor
because I think God wants me to see my doctor!
That is why the more I call His name, the more the headache!
He wants me to go and see my doctor!
If not, He will answer my prayer!"
You see, many Christians today, when trouble is far, they are good in calling the name Jesus.
Like you learn that there is a war somewhere - far.
You read it on the pages of a newspaper; you saw it on a channel.
There is a war somewhere - far.
Now, you want to pray to stop the war.
"Hey, Jesus Christ, that war there should stop there, should just stop!"
By the time you open your eyes, you find that the war is just at your door.
The trouble you are trying to stop far away is now very close to your door.
This time, you will not close your eyes.
You say, "Ah! What do You want me to do?"
When faith fills our soul, it fills our soul with a strong desire
for the things we pray for.
It fills our soul with a strong desire to pray the more, even in the face of trial,
to pray the more even in the face of temptation,
to pray the more even in the face of threats to life.
Let me take you to the book of Daniel.
In Daniel 6: 10, "Now when Daniel learned that the decree had been published,
he went home to his upstairs room where the windows opened toward Jerusalem".
While the decree was published, Daniel still had that boldness to go to the upper room.
Faith fills our soul with a strong desire.
Tell your neighbour: Faith fills our soul with a strong desire.
It fills our soul with a strong desire for the things we pray for -
desire to pray the more even in the face of trouble,
to pray the more even in the face of threats to life.
Like I was telling you:
If faith affects the realm of the mind, this means
whatever we see should be examined in the light of God's Word.
Whatever we hear should be examined in the light of God's Word.
Whatever we read should be examined in the light of God's Word.
When something happens to you, whether positive or negative,
as a man of faith, it will be too soon to jubilate or despair
without finding out what God says about it.
Because faith is not only emotional but also affects the realm of the mind.
Tell your neighbour: When something happens to you, whether positive or negative,
it will be too soon to jubilate, if it is positive;
it will be too soon to despair, if it is negative,
without finding out what God says about it.
If it is positive, it will be too soon to say, "Ahh, this is money!"
because when joy is not handled carefully, it will soon turn to sadness.
Tell your neighbour: When joy is not handled carefully, it will soon turn to sadness.
When sadness is handled carefully, it will soon turn to joy.
How you handle your situation matters as a man of faith.
God sometimes uses foolish things to confound the wise.
To the wise, poverty is a foolish thing.
To the wise, sickness is a foolish thing.
To the wise, barrenness is a foolish thing.
To the wise, nightmare is a foolish thing.
To the wise, setback is a foolish thing.
Remember, it was disappointment that preserved Peter.
Our God is an awesome God
He reigns
From Heaven above with wisdom, power and love
Our God is an awesome God
He reigns
From Heaven above with wisdom, power and love
Our God is an awesome God
He reigns
From Heaven above with wisdom, power and love
Our God is an awesome God
Amen!
Yes.
If you must have faith, you must learn to hear God's Word.
It is important for you to not only hear it with your ears, but also with your heart.
With your what? - Heart.
To hear God's Word in our heart requires openness and hunger for God's Word.
When you are hungry for God's Word - it means your life depends on knowing it.
If your life does not depend on knowing God's Word, you cannot be hungry for it.
You cannot.
And your life can only depend on knowing it when you have love for it, time for it.
When you learn to hear God's Word, you have affection for it.
Through hearing, belief comes.
Through believing, trust comes.
Through trusting, confidence is established.
Now, in conclusion.
Yes.
This process is not automatic - the process of hearing and obeying.
I said, through hearing, belief comes.
Through believing, trust comes.
Through trusting, confidence is established.
This process is not automatic but gradual.
However, this process is not automatic but gradual.
What do I mean?
I mean, those who refuse to take these tiny steps cannot believe God.
Take note of that.
Those who refuse to take these tiny steps cannot believe God.
Because they cannot understand the basic truth about faith.
Look at what happened to the boy's father.
Among the crowd, the boy's father put to shame the faithless generation with his belief and prayer.
These two things.
It was not automatic.
"I believe, help my unbelief!"
That is not automatic. If it were automatic, "I believe" and you would just receive.
He said, "I believe". At the same time he withdrew, "Ah, help my unbelief".
Let's take you there.
Mark 9:24, "Immediately the boy's father shouted,
"I do believe; help me overcome my unbelief!"
Now, there are two statements there.
With his belief and prayer saying, "I do believe; help me overcome my unbelief!"
He put to shame the faithless generation with his belief.
Remember, with his belief; that is, traditional belief.
Because he said, "I believe" and later he said, "Help me overcome my unbelief!".
It means, that belief he claimed at the beginning was unable to receive from Jesus
because believing is the condition to receive.
Now, we say with his belief and prayer.
This statement is both an expression of his belief in our Lord Jesus Christ and prayer for help.
It was that faith that found expression in the spoken word.
Let me take you to Genesis 1:3,
"God said, 'Let there be light', and there was light".
Wow.
That command was an expression of God's faith in Himself.
Back to Mark 11.
If I may read verse 23.
"I tell you the truth, if anyone says to this mountain, 'Go, through yourself into the sea' --"
Be thou removed!
It was God's faith in Himself.
That is God in action.
When the believer says, "In the name of Jesus, be thou removed!",
it is an expression of the believer's faith in God.
Let me take you to the book of Acts 3.
"Then Peter said, 'Look at us!'"
That is all!
That is the part I need.
"Then Peter said, 'Look at us!'"
What does that mean?
That is attention!
I mean, genuine willingness.
Look at, "Pay attention to God's Word because God is in His Word".
"Then Peter said, 'Look at us!'"
It means, "Attention, please!"
If you must have faith - I'm telling you how to have faith - you must pay attention.
I mean, genuine willingness.
Genuine willingness means you must forget yourself.
How do we forget ourselves?
We forget ourselves when we leave it for God.
Tell your neighbour: Leave it for God!
We pay attention when we leave it for God.
Say, leave it for God!
Leave your trouble for God,
your worry for God!
Leave it for God!
God is aware.
He is aware of your injustice.
He will not leave you without justice.
He is aware of your sickness.
He will not leave you without healing.
He is aware of your yoke.
He will not leave you without freedom.
He is aware of your failure.
He will not leave you without success.
He is aware! Say, He is aware!
Leave it for God!
Leave it for God
Don't worry yourself
Don't cry no more
Jesus is alive
Praise God!
You can face tomorrow
He understands
What you are passing through today
Let God glorify His name
Don't worry; leave it for God.
Your failure - leave it for God. Your poverty - leave it for God.
Your nightmare - leave it for God. Your trouble - leave it for God.
Your panic - leave it for God.
Leave it for God!
This is the only way you can have faith - leave it for God and stay focused!
You cannot show genuine willingness if you don't leave it for God.
It is either you are yes or no.
You cannot be yes and no.
It is either you are righteous or unrighteous.
There is no neutral kingdom.
God is able
Abundantly able
To deliver and to save
God is able
Abundantly able
To deliver those who trust in Him
Underline the word 'trust'.
If you trust Him, you leave your worry for Him.
If you trust God, you leave your failure for Him.
If you trust Him, you leave your panic for Him.
If you trust Him, you leave your barrenness, your nightmare for Him.
I have confidence in His ability to heal, to bless, to save.
If you believe Him, you must have confidence in His ability.
"Then Peter said, 'Look at us!'"
You know what Peter was saying?
He was saying, he should leave his worry for God and look at him.
To know Jesus is not only to see His works but to learn His way.
To know Jesus is not only to see His miracles but also to learn His way.
To know Jesus Christ is not only to see His works but also to learn His way.
Thank you very much, in Jesus' name!
WHAT IS FAITH? Teaching With T.B. Joshua
Amen!
Thank you very much!
Rise up. Let me just give you a word of prayer.
Jesus must be honoured
In my life every day
Right now, bow down your head.
Ask Jesus to give you a hearing heart.
I've got my mind made up
And I won't turn back
Because I want to see my Jesus some day
I've got my mind made up
And I won't turn back
Because I want to see my Jesus some day
Father, we thank You.
Give thanks to Him for giving you an obedient heart, faithful heart.
Give thanks to Him. Father, we thank You.
Holy Spirit, we thank You.
Accept our thanks, in Jesus' name.
Thank You, Lord.
We believe you have been inspired by the clip you have just watched.
Click here to subscribe to witness more of God's power at work in our generation today
and stay up-to-date with the latest prophecies, deliverances,
sermons and testimonies from The SCOAN.
Emmanuel TV - Changing Lives, Changing Nations, and Changing the World.
RV: Mel Flowers 17/03/2019